hello this video is going to be an
overview and introduction to chapter 9
on model based analysis in par Missoula
and friston octave inference 2022
textbook so I'll read the opening quote
and then Ali feel free to give a first
thought or overview on the chapter just
because we have the best Hammer does not
mean that every problem is an ale Barack
Obama
so what is your overview on chapter nine
okay so chapter nine as the title
suggests is about doing uh
is about introducing an approach to data
analysis specifically uh model based
data analysis because as we know there
are multiple different approaches to do
any kind of analysis and data uh so
there are approaches that are basically
model free or model without any specific
models and we just do some uh some
techniques on data wrangling and and the
data directly dated directly but in this
chapter
um there is this approach
that that is inspired by active
inference
um framework that's basically uh is uh
is about how to uh organize or how to
interpret uh basically the data we have
at hand using active inference framework
so this kind of model based analysis can
be used on many different scenarios
involving uh Empirical research in which
uh some uh some raw data has been
gathered and we need to make sense of
those data in terms of uh what active
inference models can be applied or can
be appropriate to organize those data
and what kind of inference can we get by
developing a kind of active input model
and basically
treating the data as the input to the
model and then to see what kind of
imprints we can get using those data G
great thank you
they write here in this chapter we focus
on the ways in which active inference
can be applied in understanding
empirical data and the point you ended
with is exactly the point that I like to
highlight which is that up to this point
in the textbook the examples have all
been proposed basically from scratch
like the rat and the teammates or the
frog jumping out of the hand and so
first there was the conceptualization of
a generative model here in this textbook
to kind of demonstrate some feature of
active inference framework and then data
could be generated from the model
whereas in chapter nine we're thinking a
lot more about the back and forth
between the generative model and the
data including situations where we begin
with a given data structure and then
construct a generative model to analyze
that in different ways that we'll cover
okay section 9.2 meta Bayesian methods
what would you say about metabayesian
methods
all right so uh this particular figure
on this page figure 9.1 uh tends to be
one of the figures uh that we
um come time and time again uh when we
refer to kind of meta modeling go back
to the meta modeling aspect of uh active
inference so basically
um in this kind of view of active
inference uh it is
I mean
it can be used to model a kind of nested
hierarchical models of different sorts
so basically it's a kind of
self-referential way of modeling a
situation of interest in other words
instead of just uh modeling a system of
Interest we can also apply the same
mathematical technology on the same
theoretical framework to model the The
Observer of that phenomena or
let's say the scientist or the age agent
that that
intends to study that phenomena in other
words it's a kind of uh it's a way to
kind of formalize
[Music]
a specific way of doing a scientific
research
um in terms of doing uh these this kind
of self-reflective or recursional way of
meta modeling so
in this section of chapter nine uh there
are some discussions and also references
to many different papers that
use this kind of process as this
self-referential process of metabasian
modeling to model many many different
scenarios so as we see in figure one 9.1
if we take the subjective model as the
kind of graph based graph
Bayesian graph that we've seen before in
previous chapters and then take that
exact same model and put it in
as the input to the system we can
on the outer level of this nested
hierarchy look at this
as the subject of interest and then
apply the exact same mathematical
formalism to model this phenomena as
well
great inside of the box here is the
system of Interest this is the subject
of the experiment this is the rat and
the Maze whose generative model
describes observations and hidden States
through time and policy conditioned upon
the parameterization of the model and
then outside of that cognitive model
which may well be a map of its
surrounding we have the experimenters
room with the stimuli that is being
passed in it's a policy selection from
the experimenter but it's an observation
coming in from the perspective of the
subject and then the actions coming out
of the generative model at the heart of
this image is taken up to be objective
behavioral data by the experimenter and
there's a really interesting point that
they make about two reasons why you
might want to fit a computational model
to observe Behavior
the first is to estimate parameters of
interest that explain a given particular
things Behavior or differentiate groups
or subtypes of similar things
that's computational phenotyping
so that is conditioning upon a
structural model looking to
differentiate individuals or an
individual through time or across
contexts and conversely you might fix
upon one individual or a group of
individuals and be interested to test
different hypotheses about the
underlying cognitive structures
section 9.3 variational oh yeah please
good
yeah and also one other point that might
be worth mentioning here is
um this recent development in Bayesian
mechanics literature and specifically uh
the proof that the cmap a way of uh
looking at the phenomena uh is the exact
Duel of the fep uh way of modeling the
same
the same state space so uh in this way
cmap and fep Duality can be mapped onto
this self-referential way of metabasian
metamasian modeling because on the one
hand if we are if we look at the
environment or the system of interest
from the Viewpoint of the system we were
basically dealing with fep but if we
flip that logic around we're dealing
with cmap or strength maximum entropy
principle so yeah that was
also I think relevant to metabasian or
phenotypic computation as well
cool
anything to say on 9.3
variational LaPlace and 9.4 parametric
empirical days
okay so these two sections are pretty
technical uh but there's this recent
paper I think it was published uh a
couple of weeks ago by first at all
which provides a tutorial on variation
on LaPlace variational techniques uh
which I think can greatly help to
understand uh or to unpack some of the
dense technicalities of this section in
this particular section 9.3 so I highly
recommend looking at that paper before
or alongside reading this section as
well uh yeah exactly
so
yes
those are two technical sections as you
brought up exactly 9.5 the instructions
for model base analysis
here they're going to outline some steps
to analyze empirical behavioral data
Choice data using active inference step
one collect behavioral data Step 2
formulate a pomdp partially observable
Markov decision process step 3 specify a
likelihood function
step four specify prior beliefs step 5
solve for posterior probability and
model evidence and step six perform
group level analysis this is summarized
in figure 9.2 what would you say about
this process
uh okay so I believe this is a kind of
common process used in SPM 12 so
um well it it helps to look at this
process in terms of the recipe provided
in chapters chapter 6 and also used
extensive mean and modeling the behavior
modeling the cases in chapters seven and
eight but basically uh those I mean this
kind of routine again is not something I
believe that needs to be followed
precisely in every detail but
it can be modified based on the scenario
we're interested in so at least that's
my understanding of these routines or
recipes or whatever we want to call them
so but it provides a helpful starting
point uh which can
help to at least
begin to sketch some uh some routes
through our modeling uh modeling task
without losing uh the forest for the
trees
so
yep
I would describe this figure as
connecting the empirical structure of
the data so in this case it'd be the
location of the animal in the tmas
Through Time
connecting the empirical data structure
to a generative model that graciously
receives that data without any false
positives or false negatives that's
where we get the kind of nice fitting
design and the category Theory
plus specification of some of the
accessory Machinery that's required for
the Bayesian statistical model
and then
stage six here is like a figure that
you'd see in a paper if there were some
parameter in the pomdp that described
the mouse's skittishness or its boldness
and that parameter was going to be
identified and then to go from the
parameter to generated data that would
be the kind of generative direction or
in the recognition Direction with the
inverted model you could go from
empirical data to identification of
parameters and so maybe this graph in
six represents 10 mice per replicate and
the parameterization of each of their
parameters related to some personality
trait or performance on a task and then
these bar charts could be
straightforwardly compared using an
anova or t-test and that would basically
be the paper we designed the experiment
we designed the generative model we did
statistics here's the statistical
outcomes that we identified in terms of
here group differences from these five
groups
section 9.6 provides examples of
generative models they provide in figure
9.3 in overview
these are two different generative
models of icicade motor Behavior
epistemically driven
and there's more that could be said but
this highlights to me that there's
always a plurality of generative models
that can be drawn even for the same
behavior and this point is made
especially clear because on the left the
experiment of atoms at all is performs
with A continuous time continuous space
model whereas the Mirza on the right was
in a categorical space and discrete time
anything else to say about this setting
other than that it was used to cite
these papers and give examples of what
it looks like to connect a generative
model here of isocades and vision to
empirical data
so I think that's pretty much all there
is to it but uh again there are some
subtle differences uh between those two
examples in terms of how those
generative models
um are conceived so uh it's helpful to
see uh two related examples
um I mean they're both about studying
the eye movement but different aspects
of it so these kinds of subtleties
can rise in a real real world situations
when we want to when we deal with
empirical data various types so I
believe uh these two examples are very
clever cleverly chosen to point some of
the subtleties of modeling here cool
section 97 models of false inference the
section among other things contains a
table of various settings that have been
studied using active inference in the
computational pathology space and the
pathologies listed here with citations
and a little bit of a note are addiction
impulsivity and compulsivity delusions
hallucinations
interpersonal and personality disorders
ocular motor syndromes pharmacotherapy
and prefrontal syndromes visual neglect
and disorders of interceptive inference
under the section header of
models of false inference what would you
say about this
okay so I believe it links to recent
developments and this new area of
computational Psychiatry because
unlike the traditional psychiatry in
this new way of studying some abnormal
behavior
researchers try to develop computational
models in order to model the normal
human behavior and then study how
quote-unquote false inferences can arise
from those normal models and then try to
map this kind of behavior onto various
types of abnormal behavior abnormal
psychiatric disorders so
uh this can be a kind of introduction to
this new research discipline and also uh
I I'd like to uh point to Kristen's
um review paper and I think it was
published in nature a few months ago
about computational Psychiatry so in
that paper there are many more examples
and other more many more details about
how exactly those kind of computational
models are constructed in order to study
uh those disorders
right and then and the interesting
discussion we always have about what is
the relationship between Bayes optimal
generative models the ball rolling
downhill things unfolding as they do in
a setting and pathology and what does
pathology mean what is an average what's
a false
belief or a hallucination in this
setting and then 9.8 it's a very short
summary
they provide the six steps in figure 9.1
providing a generic method for Designing
experiments
and there's a lot of opportunities to
ask different sorts of questions
analogously to chapter five studying the
mammalian nervous system here they
highlighted their most active area of
work which is on human computational
pathology
any other comments on chapter nine
uh nothing particular comes to mind
currently so